NYSUT General Officers Audio-Visual Materials 6174/017 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT General Officers Audio-Visual Materials
1972-1999
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/017 AV
0.94 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Audio cassette tapes, audio open-reel tapes, video cassette tapes.
7544264
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 01, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 06, 2014
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Scope and Contents
Training tapes and newsclips on topics such as shared decision making and social promotion; speeches by Al Shanker and Tom Hobart, and excerpts from NYSTA House of Delegates conferences (1972) and later events to 1999. Includes open-reel audio tapes, audio cassettes, and VHS.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/017: NYSUT General Officers Records 6174/017 MB: NYSUT General Officers Memorabilia. 6174/017 P: NYSUT General Officers Photographs All other 6174 collections
Teachers' unions -- New York (State); New York State United Teachers
7544264
- Effective Classroom Management (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  VHS Tape
- Shared Decision Making Workshop Educational Conference, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  VHS Tape. May 11, 1988
- Social Promotion WTEN News Ten Albany, NY, Newscast, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  VHS Tape. January 20, 1999
- An Overview of the Task Force on the Teaching Profession: The New York Report: A Blueprint for Learning and Teaching, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  VHS Tape. March 1988
- NYSUT School Restructuring Project Prototype, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  VHS Tape. September 18, 1992
- First Things First: Lessons for Life (Box 1, Folder 6)
- AFT Convention 1994 Leadership Development Task Force Presentation (Box 1, Folder 7)
- NYSUT Standard, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  VHS Tape. April 20, 1997
- The Struggle for Teachers Rights, Greenburgh Eleven Federation of Teachers, Childrens Village (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Do We Still Need School Boards? Albert Shanker, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Audio Cassette
- House of Delegates, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Audio Cassette. June 17, 1972
- NYSTA Delegation Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Audio Cassette. June 27, 1972
- Third Business Meeting, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Audio Cassette. June 29, 1972
- Hobart Address 1975 RA (Box 1, Folder 14)
  7" open reel audio tape. March 21, 1975
- Al Shanker 1975 RA (Box 1, Folder 15)
  7" open reel audio tape.